Guide to the Mary Hitchcock Wilde papers, 1801-1984.
Wilde, Mary Hitchcock papers, 1801-1984
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Mary Hitchcock Wilde papers, 1801-1984.
3989
Mary Hitchcock Wilde.
6.7 cubic ft.
Papers, clippings, publications, writings, correspondence, photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Letters, photographs and photograph albums, writings and genealogical material of Hitchcock-Wilde and related families including Fairbrothers, Frost, Mann, Marvin, Raymond, Reynolds, Stenson, and Waddy.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Mary Hitchcock Wilde, 1905-1984, graduated from the New Jersey College for Women and received a Ph.D. in botany from Cornell University in 1942.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Letters, photographs and photograph albums, writings and genealogical material of Hitchcock-Wilde and related families including Fairbrothers, Frost, Mann, Marvin, Raymond, Reynolds, Stenson, and Waddy. Letters, writings, and papers concern the military career of Captain Stephen Henry Hitchcock (1808-1857) who aided in the Texas war for independence from Mexico and to the land he acquired in Texas. Reynolds family papers (1837-1893) are mainly letters of Mary Ann Hitchcock and her son Lieutenant Edward McDonald. Wilde family papers are from William Raymond Wilde (1861-1926), and Mary Louise Stenson Wilde (1883-1959), parents of Mary Hitchcock Wilde.
Papers of Mary Hitchcock Wilde include writings as a child; student writings published in The Budget, school magazine of The Vail-Deane School in Elizabeth, N.J.; other published and unpublished writings; personal correspondence; financial records; and correspondence with Arthur Johnson Eames, and other botanists in regard to research on gymnosperms; also, correspondence and records pertaining to the Eames Memorial Fund; and photographs of Wilde's furnishings used as an inventory after her death. In addition, there are diplomas, certificates, indentures, calling cards, greeting cards, auction catalogs, and other memorabilia.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Wilde, Mary Hitchcock.; Eames, Arthur Johnson, 1881-; Fairbrothers family.; Frost family.; Hitchcock family.; Hitchcock, Mary Ann.; Hitchcock, Stephen Henry.; Mann family.; Marvin family.; McDonald, Edward.; Raymond family.; Reynolds family.; Stenson family.; Waddy family.; Wilde family.; Wilde, Mary Louise Stenson.; Wilde, William Raymond.; Cornell University.; New Jersey College for Women.; Vail-Deane School.
Subjects:
Family--New Jersey--Bayonne.; Gymnosperms.; Botany.; Children's writings.; Botanists.; Women scientists.
Places:
Texas--History--Revolution, 1835-1836.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Papers of Hitchcock, Reynolds, Wilde Families
Boxes 1-4
Series II. Mary Hitchcock Wilde Papers
Boxes 5-7
Series III. Hitchcock-Wilde Family Photographs and Other Items
Boxes 8-20, mapcase
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Papers of Hitchcock, Reynolds, Wilde Families
  - William M. Hitchcock - Masonic Certificate, 1801 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hitchcock Family Papers, 1823-1839 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hitchcock Family Papers, 1840-1853 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hitchcock Family Papers, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters re Stephen Henry Hitchcok's Military Career (recommendations, etc.), 1834-1842 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - List of Volunteers to Aid Texas under command of Capt. S. Henry Hitchcock, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Commissions, etc. - Texas Army Muster Roll, Second Company raised in New York City, 1836-1844; 1851 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - S. Henry Hitchcock Letters, 1825-1842; 1856 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - S. Henry Hitchcock Letters to Father, William M. Hitchcock, 1839-1841 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - S. Henry Hitchcock re Texas land, 1840-1857 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - S. Henry Hitchcock Writings (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cornelia Hitchcock Liborius, 1824-1877 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Clara Hitchcock Flanders, 1857-1918 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Emily Hitchcock Letters, 1846-1865; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Emily Hitchcock calling cards, copper plate (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Emily Hitchcock copy and composition books and clippings, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Reynolds Family Papers, 1837-1849 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Reynolds Family Papers, Jan. 1850-July 1850 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Reynolds Family Papers, Aug. 1850-Dec. 1850 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Reynolds Family Papers, 1851-1864 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Reynolds Family Papers, 1860-1864; Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Reynolds Family Papers, 1882-1893 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Reynolds, Wilde, etc. - miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Wilde Family, 1840-1903; Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - William B. Wild(e) Sketchbook, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - William B. Wild(e) Music (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Wilde Family Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - William R. Wilde re S.H. Hitchcock heirs, land, 1904-1906 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - William R. Wilde Letters, 1904-1910, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - William R. Wilde Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Wilde Honeymoon Scrapbook, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Mr. and Mrs. William R. Wilde, 1904-1919 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Mr. and Mrs. William R. Wilde and Mary Hitchcock Wilde (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - William R. Wilde - Will, 1920-1926 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - William R. Wilde - Poetry, book list (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mary Louise Stenson Wilde and Mary, 138-1943 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mary Louise and Mary, 1952-1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Stenson Whitney Rogers - Will, genealogy, notes (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Notes: Waddy, Wilde Families (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - George A. Waddy: Will, obituaries (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Cards, bookmarks, etc. - hand-crafted (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Heirlooms and Objects of Interest" (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous: Greeting Cards, etc. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Texas Centinel" newspaper, September 9, 1841 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "The Grand Army of the Republic", July 1867 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Staten Island - history (clippings), 1890, 1893, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1836, 1844, 1865, 1881 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Exculpation of U.S. Marine Corps in Mexico," Major John G. Reynolds - clippings, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Genealogical Material (Box 4, Folder 8-12)
- Series II. Mary Hitchcock Wilde Papers
  - Writings
    - Vail-Deane Budget (school publication), Vol. XXII no. 3, June 1919 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Vail-Deane Budget (school publication), Vol. XXIII no. 2, Apr. 1920 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Vail-Deane Budget (school publication), Vol. XXV no. 3, June 1921 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Vail-Deane Budget (school publication), Vol. XXVI no. 3, June 1922 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Vail-Deane Budget (school publication), Vol. XXVII no. 1, Dec. 1922 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Vail-Deane Budget (school publication), Vol. XXVII no. 2, Apr. 1923 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Vail-Deane Budget (school publication), Vol. XXVII no. 3, June 1923 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Vail-Deane Budget (school publication), Vol. XXVIII no. 2, Marc. 1924 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Vail-Deane Budget (school publication), Vol. XXVIII no. 3, May 1924 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Vail-Deane Budget (school publication), Vol. XXIX no. 1, Dec. 1924 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Vail-Deane Budget (school publication), Vol. XXIX no. 2, Mar. 1925 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Vail-Deane Budget (school publication), Vol. XXIX no. 3, May 1925 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Vail-Deane Budget (school publication), Vol. XXX no. 1, Dec. 1925 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Vail-Deane Budget (school publication), Vol. XXX no. 2, Mar. 1926 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Vail-Deane Budget (school publication), Vol. XXX no. 3, May 1926 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - "My Life," 1920 - Story of young daughter of "Earl of Arundel," illustrated with photographs of dolls (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - "Literary Accomplishments Book II" with some illustrations (drawings), 1919-1923 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - "Literary Accomplishments Book III" with some illustrations (drawings), 1923-1925 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - "Memoirs of a Young Girl", Aug. 1924 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - "Dream Divine," with Mr. Burrows' Criticism, 1933-1934 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - "Covenant with Time," original illuminated manuscript, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Story 1 - The Dream Divine, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Lesson 1, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Story 2 - Behind the Fog, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Lesson 2, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Story 3 - The Empty Room, Dr. Hodett's and Mr.Bower's Criticism, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Lesson 3, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Lesson 4, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Story 4 - Mademoiselle, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Manuscript of Wilde - New Jersey College, c. 1936 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - English H3 - Carbon copies of lessons and letters to Dr. Hodett, 1936-1937 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Flight of the Sparrow, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Knight of the Lost Cause, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Notes for Children of Earth part 1 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Notes for Children of Earth part 2 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Notes for Children of Earth part 3 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Notes for Children of Earth (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Notes for Children of Earth (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Manuscript: Children of Earth Chapter I, II (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Manuscript: Children of Earth Chapter III, IV (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Manuscript: Children of Earth Chapter V, plus (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Thoughts - pen and ink drawings (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Reference notes for book "To Be What I Desire" (Esse Quod Opto) (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Gleanings - manuscripts, drawings, etc. (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Poems (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Personal Papers
    - Transcripts, 1930-1937 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Membership in honor societies, 1930-1950 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Record of Training, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - New Jersey College for Women, etc. (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence, 1940-1948 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Letters - Alice Sadtler, 1948-1983 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Postal cards to (Aunt) Rosalie C. Wilde during Mary's European trip to Botanical Congress, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Botanical Congress, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Letters - Dr. Vivia B. Appleton - also, A Doctor's Letters from China Fifty Years Ago, by Appleton, 1971-1977 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Passports, 1950, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Postal Cards - trip to West Indies (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - "Business Letters" and miscellany (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - "Business Letters" and miscellany (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Christmas Cards, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Estate, Will (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Obituaries, biography, material related to memorial service, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Papers related to cemetery plots, Staten Island (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - "Shell on Windows," 5 Cornell Walk, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Landscape Planting Plan, 5 Cornell Walk, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - House - correspondence, plans, blueprints, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Travel Itineraries - Historic Ithaca, 1979-1982 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - "Among maps and papers that she took with her on vacation to Florida", 1984 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Financial Papers and Miscellaneous
    - "Library Catalogue and values - partial list of furniture", 1913-1918 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Disposal of property, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - "Christie's Auction Catalog: Sale of Mary's antique furniture and silver, Japanese prints, Chinese porcelains, fine old furnishings" (Box 6, Folder 21-24)
    - Blue Cross and Medicare (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Blue Cross Instructions (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Sigma Xi Hospital Insurance - claims (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Sigma Xi Hospital Insurance Plan (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Social Security (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - TIAA (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Books- Bills (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Bills, receipts, 1969; 1970 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Bills, receipts, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Bills, receipts, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Bills, receipts, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Bills, receipts, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Bills, receipts, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Bills, receipts, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Bills, receipts, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Bills, receipts, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Bills, receipts, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Bills, receipts, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Bills, receipts, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Bills, receipts, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Miscellany (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Miscellany and Irish Postal Cards - souvenirs from The Irish Industrial Exposition, 1905 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Miscellaneous - Texas Western College, El Paso (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Stocks, bonds, etc. (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Eames-Wilde Research
    - Report of the Opening of the Botanical Laboratories, University of Toronto; also, letters from R.B. Thompson, 1927, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Conifers - correspondence, 1942-1955 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Eames - Letters to Wilde, 1943-1951 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Eames: "Gymnosperms" Introductory Preface, early draft, correspondence, 1946-1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Eames: retirement program, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Eames: Gynmosperm correspondence, 1962-1966 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Carl Wilson's tribute to Eames, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Eames: biographical material, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Eames: biography by Wilde, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Arthur Johnson Eames Memorial Fund
    - Eames Botanical Preserve, 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Eames Botanical Preserve, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Eames Memorial Fund, 1972-1983 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Eames Memorial Fund records, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Eames Memorial Fund records, 1969-1977 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Eames Memorial Fund records (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Natural Areas Sub-committee, 1976-1983 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Dr. Vivia Appleton, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Dr. Vivia Appleton - news clippings (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Dr. Lawrence H. MacDaniels, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - News clippings - proposed route 13 and others (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Series III. Hitchcock-Wilde Family Photographs and Other Items
  - Eames-Wilde Research
    - William Raymond Wilde (?), 1892-1896 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - "Pictures of Ireland taken Apr. 1901 " (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - William Raymond Wilde pre- 1905, Undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - "Mary Hitchcock Wilde - Daughter of Mary Louise and William Raymond Wilde", 1905-1913 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Wilde Family, 1915-1922 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Mary Hitchcock Wilde, 1924-1935 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - "My School-Day Memory Book," inscribed "Mother to Sweetness", 1925-1962 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Other Items
    - Pamphlet: A Conclusive Exculpation of the Marine Corps in Mexico... by Brevet-Major John G. Reynolds, 1852 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Navy Register of the United States, 1855 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Receipt Book - William Mann Hitchcock, 1809-1825 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - William R. Wilde Diary, 1892-1935 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Keepsake box fashioned as Shakespeare's Comedies containing holiday greetings and other miscellaneous items (Box 20)
  - Wilde-Hitchcock and Related Families Photographs
    - Family Photographs: Fairbrothers, Rogers, Stenson, Waddy (Box 9)
    - Family Photographs: Flanders, Frost, Hitchcock, Reynolds, Stenson, Wilde; also, Long Island, homes (Box 10)
    - Family Photographs: Frost, Hitchcock, Raymond, Wilde; also homes (Box 11)
    - Glass-frame Photographs: Frost, Hitchcock, Wilde - FRAGILE (Box 12)
    - Daguerreotypes, framed photos, glass negatives: Dallimore, Flanders, Hitchcock, Raymond, Reynolds, Salmon, Stenson, Vail, Wilde - FRAGILE (Box 13)
    - Mary H. Wilde photographs re botany, Cornell University, etc. (Box 14)
    - Mary H. Wilde photographs and slides (Box 15)
    - Mary H. Wilde - photographs of 5 Cornell Walk, and of furnishings, used as inventory (Box 16)
  - Photographs, Certificates and other, rolled
    - Naturalization Papers - William Basil Wild(e), 1880 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Certificate of Marriage - William Stenson and Lucia Laura Waddy, 1883 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Certificate - Mary Louise Stenson - American Flag House and Betsy Ross Memorial Association, 1899 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Certificate of Marriage - William Raymond, 1904 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Certificate - William R. Wilde - The Lincoln Farm Association, 1906 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Certificate/Diploma - Vail-Deane School, 1926 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Navigational Chart - Kill Van Kull, NY-NJ, 1917 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Photograph - Vail Deane School group, 1921 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Photograph - Botanical Society Banquet, 1940 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Citation and Certificate - Phi Beta Kappa, 1946 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Set Up of "In Memoriam" (Mary H. Wilde), 1984 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Register of Pedigree - Hitchcock Family (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Mary Hitchcock Wilde postal cards and commercial slides (Box 18)
    - Scapulary "found in the chapel attached to the church situated at 'Hacienda Tacubuya'..." - see description in 2-6; Bead bag brought from either Texas or Mexico, see description in 1-8 (Box 19)
    - The Decalogue written by Stephen H. Hitchcock, Dec. 25, 1820 (Mapcase-folder 1, Folder 1)
    - Muster roll of men under S. Henry Hitchcock, 1837 (Mapcase-folder 2)
    - Indentures - Texas, 1842, 1846, 1855 (Mapcase-folder 3)
    - Indenture - John Hinton-Esther Wild, St. George Hanover Square, County of Middlesex, 1823 (Mapcase-folder 4)
    - Co. E. 13 - Regiment - Resolution of Condolence: Ernest Liborius, Brooklyn, NY, killed by mine explosion in attack on Petersburg, Va. New York Herald, Nov. 1864 (Mapcase-folder 5)
    - Rutgers-New Jersey College Diploma, 1930 (Mapcase-folder 6)
    - Rutgers-New Jersey College Diploma, 1932 (Mapcase-folder 7)
    - Cornell University Ph.D. Diploma, 1942 (Mapcase-folder 8)